[Music]
across the board a series of studies
published in the annals of internal
medicine found a statistically
significant association between lower
consumption of red and processed meats
and lower total mortality meaning living
a longer life lower cardiovascular
disease mortality as well as lower risk
of dying from cancer yet remarkably the
authors of these studies concluded that
people should ignore all the other
dietary guidelines and keep eating meat
to their heart's content
or rather discontent
they offered three reasons why their
panel reached a conclusion at odds with
other contemporary dietary guidelines
that advise people to cut down on meat
one reason
is taste in short people who enjoy
eating meat enjoy eating meat i did a
whole video on this
but in short taste preference probably
shouldn't be a major factor in
developing dietary guidelines
many people don't want to quit smoking
stop drinking or exercise more but that
doesn't change the science i shouldn't
change the public health recommendations
a second reason they explain why their
recommendations differ from everyone
else's is that other guidelines didn't
use the so-called grade approach
no wonder since grade was mainly
developed for evaluating evidence from
drug trials
there are grading systems for diet and
lifestyle approaches but the meat panel
chose to inappropriately apply grade
which could similarly be misused to
undermine recommendations about tobacco
air pollution trans fats you name it and
i've got
three videos delving deep into all that
but this video is about the third reason
they give for ignoring meat reduction
advice other guidelines didn't highlight
the very small magnitude of the meat
effects in other words even if meat does
cause heart disease cancer diabetes and
death it doesn't cause that many heart
attacks doesn't kill that many people
cause that much cancer to offset all the
juicy taste benefits
of course it matters what people replace
the meat with replacing even
three percent of calories from animal
protein with plant protein is linked to
living longer but eggs were the worst
yes replacing red meat protein with
plant protein sources may lower overall
mortality more than 10 percent but
getting rid of egg protein and we're
talking more than
20 percent lower risk of premature death
so if someone reduces meat consumption
by swapping a burger for an egg salad
sandwich that
particular reduction in meat could mean
more mortality
but maybe they concluded there was such
a small effect only because major bodies
of evidence were omitted and relevant
studies excluded because the authors
didn't like the results
it's not that there aren't tons of
randomized controlled trials about meat
it's just that they appeared to cherry
pick a few to fit their agenda discarded
studies that even met their own criteria
and wrongly rejected randomized
controlled trials clearly showing that
meat increased risk factors like
cholesterol or blood pressure like
why wasn't predimed included or the
literally hundreds of randomized trials
on the dash diet
what about the leon diet heart study
which involved randomizing individuals
to a more mediterranean diet with a
significant drop in meat consumption
compared to the control group they
experienced a 70 percent reduction in
mortality from all causes put together
why did they exclude that study
they excluded it because in their words
it reported an
implausibly large treatment effect
in other words it worked too well
no surprise given that this so-called
nutrex meat panel was partnered with and
had multiple people on the payroll of
texas a m agrilife which receives
literally millions of dollars in meat
industry money every year
so you probably won't be shocked to find
out they also excluded research
comparing health outcomes of vegetarians
to meat eaters as they described it they
were interested in realistic decreases
in meat consumption like cutting down
three servings a week
in fact the study that they mostly
relied on the women's health initiative
achieved only a difference of 1.4
servings of meat per week
that could be like a half an ounce
difference in meat consumption per day
about a fifth of a hamburger
participants in the women's health
initiative reduced meat intake only
modestly resulting in a modest reduction
in mortality related to breast cancer
this finding in no way supports the
notion that there is no need to reduce
red or processed meat consumption for
good health rather it shows that modest
dietary changes
yield modest benefits as an analogy if
studies showed that modest reductions in
tobacco use yielded only modest health
benefits it would be inaccurate and
dangerous to suggest that there's no
need to reduce tobacco use for good
health
to say that small increases in meat
consumption only cause small increases
in the risk of disease
doesn't mean that eating meat is good
for you that's like saying that you know
smoking 24 cigarettes a day increases
risk of lung cancer only a little more
than smoking 20 cigarettes a day
being careful not to include any studies
that compared smoking 24 to smoking none
and then erroneously concluding that
smoking isn't that bad for your health
despite all that despite the ignoring
evidence excluding evidence the meat
panel nonetheless found entirely
consistent clinically meaningful
statistically significant adverse
effects of eating more meat and
processed meat on all-cause mortality on
cardiovascular disease on cancer and on
diabetes
that they did so despite all the
obstacles they put on the path to this
findings nearly incredible and directly
bespeaks the magnitude of adverse
effects of meat and processed meat
intake on health
based on their meta-analyses of large
cohorts dietary patterns with again just
a moderate reduction in bread and
processed meat consumption were
associated with lower total mortality by
lower cardiovascular disease mortality
by 14 percent lower cancer mortality by
and a 24 reduced risk of type 2 diabetes
we spend tens of billions of dollars a
year trying to tweak risk factors by
about this magnitude and this one
intervention a reduction in meat
consumption appears to do all those
things at the same time
i mean there are statin drugs that can
reduce heart disease risk but actually
increase risk for type 2 diabetes and
have little effect on cancer i mean if
there was a drug that did as much for
your health it would be a multi-billion
dollar blockbuster
the chair of nutrition at harvard
estimates a moderate reduction in red
meat consumption could prevent 200 000
deaths per year
now
the meat panel can call that a very
small effect if they want to but i
imagine it's no small effect to those
two hundred thousand families
the numbers they found is on par with
the amount of cancer and heart disease
attributable to second-hand smoke and
based on the same kind of studies
population studies it's not like they
randomize people to sit in smoky rooms
all day for a couple years
but no rational person who looks at the
public health data around the
effectiveness of smoke-free zones would
argue that people should continue
exposing themselves to secondhand smoke
so why do the same for red meat and
processed meat
the smoking analogy is actually a good
one imagine researchers select studies
with extremely small between group
differences in the number of cigarettes
smoked per week
they avoid any studies that actually
compare smoking to non-smoking i.e
meat-eating to vegetarian they find that
despite the small differences in
exposure there is still a clear and
consistent benefit to smoking less they
then apply methods of grading the
evidence that strongly favor randomized
trials over all other methods since
there are few if any randomized trials
of smoking they conclude that they have
very low confidence in the reliability
of their own findings on that basis they
publish guidelines recommending
that the public simply continue to smoke
after all they reason people who smoke
like smoking that really does sum up the
animal's papers in a nutshell that
reminds me of a quote from a famous
paper published in 1958 compiling all
the most poignant evidence linking
smoking and lung cancer after coming up
against those same charges of inadequate
proof
this quote could just as well have been
written about the state of science on
meat today
if the mountain of evidence they found
had been made on some new agent to which
hundreds of millions of adults had not
already been addicted and on one which
did not support a large industry skilled
in the arts of mass persuasion the
evidence for the hazardous nature of the
agent would be generally regarded as
beyond dispute
[Music]
you